today on Polar Ice creamy we are going
to talk about a sugar alcohol called
aryal the pros and cons and why you
probably should just avoid it in ice
cream we're going to start by talking
about what it is what is arrol arrol is
a sugar alcohol or a polyol which is
found in a lot of fruit and fermented
foods on an industrial scale which is
how 9 9% of us will get it it is
generally made by fermenting glucose
with yeast it also only has 0.2 calories
per gram which makes it ultra low
calorie first let's start at some
positives about arol the first one's got
to be calorie content it's ultra low
calorie so you almost can consider this
a zero calorie sugar substitute which is
excellent for those that are trying to
manage weight loss or just to be more
aware of what they're eating another
positive is it doesn't raise blood sugar
levels or insulin levels so it's also
suitable for people that suffer with
diabetes dental health is another thing
it's a big thing all over the entire
world or it should be Athol has actually
been proved to counter some of the
bacteria that cause tooth decay and it
doesn't promote tooth decay like
standard table sugar does it's also a
relatively tolerant sugar alcohol
meaning that those with a sensitive
digestive system are generally able to
tolerate this in normal amounts why is
it not very good in ice cream there are
a few reasons why it's not very good in
ice cream and those are based on two
things one arrol recrystallizes one
subjected to freezing temperatures what
this means is that you will use it in
your ice cream and it will stay lovely
and smooth for about 30 minutes and then
after that point the sugars all the
sugar alcohol granules will start to
recrystallize and what you will be left
with is a very grainy unpleasant mouth
fill ice cream to the point where I it's
just borderline inedible the second
thing is it's freezing point depressions
pack Pac it is almost three times as
strong at depressing the freezing point
compared to standard table sugar so if
you uh the standard way to calculate
this is giving table sugar a level of
100 and if it reduces the freezing point
then the number will increase if it
doesn't affect the freezing point the
number will decrease so if it's dextrose
the number is about 180 to 190 pack
which means that actually it's twice as
good at depressing freezing point than
standard table sugar
arrol 290 to
320 which means that you can only use a
maximum of 13 the amount of product in
your ice cream because it will not
freeze if you were to substitute Athol
for sugar in any sugar ice cream and use
the same amount your ice cream will not
freeze at all you can put it in your
freezer and it will stay liquid
permanently another reason why it's not
very good on ice cream is it has this
Ultra cold effect once Frozen which
means that your ice cream will come out
too cold and you'll find this sometimes
when you go and eat ice cream at a scoop
shop that doesn't know what they're
doing they're just making a bulk product
and selling it and you take a mouthful
you take a a spoonful and it's too cold
that's what this does another reason why
it's not very good in ice cream is
because you can't use very much you lose
a lot of the essential solids required
in an ice cream recipe sugar accounts
for a lot of solids in ice cream and
solids is what contributes to the mouth
feel and creaminess of an ice cream
product if you can only use 1/3 Max imum
of that then you lose all those solids
from the rest of the sugar which means
you have to get those solids from
somewhere else that's when balancing an
ice cream becomes very very difficult is
arrol a safe thing to eat currently in
20124 arrol is considered safe across
the world FDA the European Food Safety
Authority and the who all consider arrol
a safe food to consume recently there
have been some fears that Aral May
contribute to blood clots and future
heart disease so that is something that
also needs to be considered it can have
some side effects on your digestive
system for various things so you would
need to consume this in moderation but
you would need to do that with sugar
anyway so in conclusion orthol has some
positives it's good for your dental
health and reducing calorie intake but
for using your ice cream you really do
have to be careful you have to be
careful that you don't use too much and
it doesn't affect the texture of the
product that you're trying to make I get
why social media influencers want to use
this to reduce the calorie content of
their ice cream but they also don't
understand what they're doing ice cream
is a science to create something that
not only tastes good but has longevity
too there's nothing worse than going
through the effort of making an amazing
ice cream that only lasts 5 minutes
because you put it in a freezer and it
turns into junk then you have to throw
it away then it defeats the point of
using your sugar alcohol or your zero
calorie sweetener so if you're going to
if you're watching this because you like
making ice cream there are other
alternatives to using arral I would
leave this for your coffee or tea or
other baked goods if you're watching
this because you are just interested in
arthel and you're not that interested in
ice cream it's great for things like
that you can reduce your sugar
consumption without having that many
negative
effects anyway a nice simple video on
aiol a sugar alcohol how it's great for
some things and terrible for others
thanks for much for watching see you on
the next video